Richard Q. Yardley Cartoons
Richard Q. Yardley Cartoons
1941-1965
Yardley, Richard Q., 1903-1979
2 linear ft.
43 original political cartoons and 2 copies of original cartoons.
148773
Biographical History
Richard Q. Yardley (1903-1979) was an American editorial cartoonist.
Born in Baltimore, Maryland on March 11, 1903, Yardley attended the Friends School and the Maryland Institute. Yardley started as an artist-retoucher in the news department at the Baltimore Evening Sun in 1923 and moved into creating local news and commentary cartoons in 1934 for the Morning Sun.
In 1949 he became the Sun’s editorial cartoonist after Edmund Duffy’s retirement. From 1961 until 1965 Yardley also drew the daily comic strip panel, Our Ancestors which was syndicated by the Newspaper Enterprise Association. In addition to these works, his cartoons appeared in the New Yorker and the Reporter. Yardley was a member of the National Cartoonists Society, the American Association of Editorial Cartoonists and the National Press Club.
Richard Q. Yardley retired in 1972 and died on November 25, 1979.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Richard Q. Yardley Cartoons consist of 43 original political cartoons and 2 copies of cartoons. Twelve cartoons are dated and 31 cartoons are undated. One of the cartoons is signed, "W. Hogarth Yardley" and it is unknown if this cartoon was drawn by Richard Q. Yardley. Satire and sarcasm were regularly used elements in Yardley’s cartoons.
The cartoons were drawn with ink on illustration board as well as paper with traces of blue pencil visible. The cartoons vary in size.
Arrangement of the Collection
The cartoons bearing dates are arranged in chronological order. Cartoons without specific dates are arranged in alphabetical order by caption. Two copies of cartoons are located at the end of the collection.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Yardley, Richard Q., 1903-1979.; Sun (Baltimore, Md.: 1837); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.; Political cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Richard Q. Yardley, 1965.
Inventory
- Cartoons
  See below for an index to the cartoons.
  - 1941, 1 item (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
    23 Jun 1941
  - 1948, 2 items (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
    9 Apr 1948; 3 Dec 1948
  - 1955-1958, 8 items (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
    7 Jul 1955; 19 Jun 1956; 12 Sep 1956; 20 Mar 1956; 1957; 1958; 10 Jul 1958
  - 1960-1964, 3 items (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
    1960, no date; 11 Jun 1964; 18 Aug 1964; 3 Sep 1964
  - A-D, undated; 5 items (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - G-J, circa 1953; circa 1959,; undated; 5 items (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
  - L-O, circa 1965; undated; 9 items (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
  - P-V, circa 1964-1965; undated; 8 items (Oversize 1, Folder 8)
  - W, undated; 3 items (Oversize 1, Folder 9)
  - Cartoon signed W. Hogarth Yardley, 20 Feb 1950; 1 item (Oversize 1, Folder 10)
  - 2 copies of cartoons, undated; 2 items (Oversize 1, Folder 11)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Appalachia B1F5
Asia B1F7
Australia B1F9
Baker, Bobby B1F8
Beria, Lavrentiy B1F3
Berlin B1F2 B1F8
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich B1F3 B1F7
Britain B1F2 B1F3 B1F6 B1F9-B1F10
Byrnes, James B1F5
cartoons B1F3
Castro, Fidel B1F6
China B1F6-B1F7
civil rights B1F4 B1F7
communism B1F1 B1F3 B1F6
Congress B1F5 B1F7-B1F8
Cyprus B1F4
democracy B1F8
Egypt B1F3
Eisenhower, Dwight B1F4 B1F6 B1F9-B1F10
elections B1F1 B1F4 B1F5 B1F7-B1F8
farming B1F7
France B1F5 B1F8
George, James Zachariah B1F5
gold reserve B1F5
Goldwater, Barry B1F6 B1F8
Great Society B1F7
Greece B1F4
Hitler B1F1
India B1F8
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F5-B1F8
Keating, Kenneth B1F4
Kennedy, John F. B1F6
Kennedy, Robert F. B1F4 B1F8
Khrushchev, Nikita B1F3
Ku Klux Klan B1F7
Lewis, John B1F5
Lincoln, Abraham B1F8
Lodge Jr., Henry Cabot B1F8
Malenkov, Georgy B1F3
McCarthy, Joseph B1F8
McCarthyism B1F8
Medicare B1F7 B1F10
motion pictures B1F2
Napoleon B1F1
NATO B1F4
Nazism B1F1
New York B1F4
Nixon, Richard M. B1F3 B1F8 B1F10
nuclear weapons B1F6 B1F9
Organization of American States B1F6
Pakistan B1F8
progress B1F9
Queen Elizabeth II B1F6
Republican Party B1F3-B1F4 B1F8 B1F10
Rockefeller, Nelson B1F8
Russia B1F1-B1F3 B1F7
Scranton, William B1F8
Shepilov, Dmitri B1F3
social security B1F7 B1F10
space exploration B1F3
Stalin, Joseph B1F3
Stevenson, Adlai E. B1F3
taxes B1F5 B1F7
Tibet B1F7
Truman, Harry S. B1F5
Turkey B1F4
Vietnam War B1F6-B1F8
voting rights B1F7-B1F8
Wallace, George B1F7
Wallace, Henry B1F5